<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This is built from a template for a generic Internet Draft. Suggestions for
     improvement welcome - write to Brian Carpenter, brian.e.carpenter @ gmail.com -->
<!-- This can be converted using the Web service at http://xml.resource.org/experimental.html
     (which supports the latest, sometimes undocumented and under-tested, features.) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- You want a table of contents -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- Use symbolic labels for references -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<!-- This sorts the references -->
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<!-- Change to "yes" if someone has disclosed IPR for the draft -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- This defines the specific filename and version number of your draft (and inserts the appropriate IETF boilerplate -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-du-anima-an-intent-01" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="Autonomic Network Intent">Autonomic Network Intent and
    Format</title>

    <author fullname="Zongpeng Du" initials="Z." surname="Du">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus, No.156 Beiqing Road</street>

          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing, 100095</city>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>duzongpeng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Sheng Jiang" initials="S." surname="Jiang">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies Co., Ltd</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Q14, Huawei Campus, No.156 Beiqing Road</street>

          <city>Hai-Dian District, Beijing, 100095</city>

          <country>P.R. China</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jiangsheng@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Jeferson Campos Nobre" initials="J. " surname="Nobre">
      <organization>Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>

          <city>Porto Alegre</city>

          <country>Brazil</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jcnobre@inf.ufrgs.br</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Laurent Ciavaglia" initials="L." surname="Ciavaglia">
      <organization>Alcatel Lucent</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Route de Villejust</street>

          <city>Nozay 91620</city>

          <country>France</country>
        </postal>

        <email>laurent.ciavaglia@alcatel-lucent.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date day="" month="" year="2015"/>

    <area>Operations and Management</area>

    <workgroup>ANIMA WG</workgroup>

    <keyword>Autonomic Networking, Intent</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>This document describes the concept and consideration of the
      Autonomic Network Intent, and proposes a uniform format for the
      Autonomic Network Intent.</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>This document describes the concept and consideration of the
      Autonomic Network Intent, which is used to operate the Autonomic Nodes
      within Autonomic Networks. The background to Autonomic Network (AN) is
      described in <xref target="RFC7575"/> and <xref target="RFC7576"/>. A
      generic discovery and negotiation protocol (GDNP) is proposed by <xref
      target="I-D.carpenter-anima-gdn-protocol"/>, which would be used in the
      propagation of the Autonomic Network Intent.</t>

      <t>The Autonomic Network Intent should be able to be unscrambled by all
      Autonomic Nodes, although certain parts of contents may not be relevant
      to a specific Autonomic Node. The Autonomic Network Intent gives
      operational guidance for every Autonomic Node.</t>

      <t>This document also proposes a generic format for Autonomic Network
      Intent.</t>

      <t>The interface to receive or configure the Autonomic Network Intent is
      out of scope. The distribution mechanism of the Autonomic Network Intent
      is introduced in [I-D.liu-anima-intent-distribution].</t>

      <t>Note in draft: This version is preliminary. In particular, many
      design details may be subject to change until the anima specifications
      become agreed.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- intro -->

    <section title="Requirements Language and Terminology">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and
      "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"/> when they appear in ALL CAPS. When these words are
      not in ALL CAPS (such as "should" or "Should"), they have their usual
      English meanings, and are not to be interpreted as <xref
      target="RFC2119"/> key words.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Autonomic Function:">A feature or function which
          requires no configuration, and can derive all required information
          either through self-knowledge, discovery or through Intent.</t>

          <t hangText="Autonomic Node:">A node which employs exclusively
          Autonomic Functions.</t>

          <t hangText="Legacy Node:">A non-autonomic node, i.e., a node which
          employs some non-autonomic functions.</t>

          <t hangText="Autonomic Network:">A network containing exclusively
          Autonomic Nodes. It may contain one or several Autonomic
          Domains.</t>

          <t hangText="Autonomic Service Agent:">An agent implemented on an
          Autonomic Node which implements an Autonomic Function.</t>

          <t hangText="Intent:">An abstract, high level policy used to operate
          the network, quoted from <xref target="RFC7575"/>.</t>

          <t hangText="Autonomic Network Intent:">Intent that is used to
          intervene the running status of the Autonomic Network.</t>

          <t hangText="Administrative Intent:">Intent that is used to manage
          the network infrastructure.</t>

          <t hangText="Service Intent:">Intent that is used to intervene the
          network services running over the network infrastructure.</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="intent"
             title="Intervention of the Network Running by Autonomic Network Intent">
      <t>The Autonomic Network is supposed to work with minimum intervention
      from human operators. However, it is still needed to receive some form
      of guidance/information/orders in order to meet specific
      requirements.</t>

      <t>Upon receiving the Autonomic Network Intent, the Autonomic Node
      should be able to unscramble the meaning of the intent with no
      ambiguity, and act accordingly.</t>

      <t>Using this intent approach, the operator can manage the network as a
      whole, and does not need to configure specific node(s) in the network
      like what happens in the traditional NMS system. In other words, the
      operator communicates with the Autonomic Network using an abstract or
      high lever intent, and the configurations of the nodes take place
      automatically. By replacing most of the NMS jobs, intent-based
      management makes the network management work much easier than
      before.</t>

      <t>On the other sides, the intent-based and NMS-based management may
      co-exist for a long time, because autonomic behavior will be defined
      function by function. Similarly, at the beginning of defining the
      Autonomic Network Intents, the intent-based method cannot be assumed to
      cover every aspect of network management.</t>

      <t/>

      <section title="Use Cases for Autonomic Network Intent">
        <t>An example of the intent can be found in <xref
        target="I-D.jiang-anima-prefix-management"/>. Other examples include
        what kind of IGP (such as OSPF) or what kind of transport layer
        technology (such as MPLS) should be used for the autonomic domain.</t>

        <t>After these configurations in the network level, detailed
        configurations in every node are not needed; whereas, policy-based
        method will need detailed configurations for every specific node.</t>

        <t>An Intent should contains some common information that are needed
        by every intent and some specific information that influence the
        configuration of the nodes, and the detailed content and format of the
        specific part should be defined under its specific application
        environment by other documents, such as the prefix management intent
        defined in <xref target="I-D.jiang-anima-prefix-management"/>.</t>

        <t>{Editor Notes: as autonomic functions are defined one by one, the
        intent should be developed at a per need basis.}</t>

        <t>{Editor Notes: the intents introduced here look like not that
        abstract, however, it does help to make the network more autonomic,
        and reduce the configuration jobs. Maybe in future, when the autonomic
        node becomes more intelligent, some of the intents defined will
        disappear or be replaced.}</t>

        <t/>
      </section>

      <section title="Administrative Intent and Service Intent">
        <t>The Autonomic Networks are supposed to be self-managed. It includes
        managing the network infrastructure, and also the network services
        that are running over the network infrastructure. However, the network
        services have different features against network administration, as
        listed below. Hence, it may be better to organize them into separated
        Administrative Intent and Service Intent.</t>

        <t><list style="symbols">
            <t>A Service Intent may have a smaller scope than the
            Administrative Intent because only the nodes related to the
            service need to know this intent. Although it may only affect a
            few nodes, the Service Intent may also be propagated domain
            wide.</t>

            <t>A Service Intent may have a limited lifetime, while the
            Administrative Intents are normally permanent although the content
            of the Administrative Intent may be updated from time to time.</t>

            <t>There maybe are many Service Intents in the autonomic domain,
            while only one Administrative Intent for a giving Autonomic
            Service Agent.</t>
          </list></t>

        <t>{Editor notes: one possibility is to treat the Service Intent as a
        normal Intent for a certain Autonomic Service Agent, such as a
        Autonomic Service Provision Agent.}</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="prefixManageIntent"
             title="Uniform Format of the Autonomic Network Intent">
      <t>{Editor Notes: It is still remaining an open issue for the way that
      intent may be organized. Should the intent be a single one in a given AN
      domain with a hierarchical version, or multiple intents, each of which
      targets different Autonomic Service Agent? For now, the below text takes
      the later approach.}</t>

      <t>This section proposes a uniform intent format. It uses the tag-based
      format.</t>

      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Autonomic intent:">The root tag for the Autonomic
          Network Intent.</t>

          <t hangText="Intent type:">It indicates the intent type, which is
          associated with a specific Autonomic Service Agent.</t>

          <t hangText="Autonomic domain:">It indicates the domain of the
          Autonomic Network. It is also the scope of the Autonomic Network
          Intent.</t>

          <t hangText="Intent version:">It indicates the version of the
          Autonomic Network Intent. This is an important feature for
          synchronization.</t>

          <t hangText="Model version:">The version of the model used to define
          the intent.</t>

          <t hangText="Name:">The name of the intent which describes the
          intent for human operators.</t>

          <t hangText="Signature:">The signature is used as a security
          mechanism to provide authentication, integrity, and
          non-repudiation.</t>

          <t hangText="Timestamp:">The timestamp of the creation of the intent
          using the format supported by the IETF [TBC].</t>

          <t hangText="Lifetime:">The lifetime in which the intent may be
          observed. A special case of the lifetime is the definition of
          permanent intents.</t>

          <t hangText="Content:">It contains the main information of the
          intent. It may include objects, policies, goals and configuration
          data. The detailed contents and formats should be defined under
          their specific situations by documents that specifies the Autonomic
          Service Agent. Within the content, there may be sub_intents.</t>
        </list></t>

      <t/>

      <t>{Editor Notes: JSON is one of the term candidates for the Autonomic
      Network Intent format.}</t>

      <t/>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>Relevant security issues are discussed in <xref
      target="I-D.carpenter-anima-gdn-protocol"/>. The Autonomic Network
      Intent requires strong security environment from the start, because it
      would be great risk if the Autonomic Network Intent had been maliciously
      tampered. The Autonomic Intent should employ a signature scheme to
      provide authentication, integrity, and non-repudiation.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- security -->

    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document defines one new format. The IANA is requested to
      establish a new assigned list for it.</t>

      <t/>
    </section>

    <!-- iana -->

    <section anchor="ack" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>Valuable comments were received from Bing Liu and Brian
      Carpenter.</t>

      <t>This document was produced using the xml2rfc tool <xref
      target="RFC2629"/>.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- ack -->

    <section anchor="changes" title="Change log [RFC Editor: Please remove]">
      <t>draft-du-anima-an-intent-00: original version, 2015-06-11.</t>

      <t>draft-du-anima-an-intent-01: add intent use case section, add some
      elements for the format section, and coauthor Jeferson Campos Nobre and
      Laurent Ciavaglia, 2015-07-06.</t>
    </section>

    <!-- changes -->
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="References">
      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2119'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.2629'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7575'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.RFC.7576'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.jiang-anima-prefix-management'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.carpenter-anima-gdn-protocol'?>

      <?rfc include='reference.I-D.behringer-anima-autonomic-control-plane'?>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
